CHAPTER 4

Slaves from the Tamil Coast to
Long Distant Foreign Markets:
Portuguese Slave Trade with
Manila and Spanish Slave Trade
with Mexico, 1616-1704

Political changes took place in Tamil country after the defeat of the Vijayanagara ruler in the battle of Talikota in 1565. Further, new political developments also took place in Portugal after the death of King Dom Sebastiao in 1578. Philip II, the King of Spain also became the King of Portugal in 1580. As a result he introduced new policies for global trade. At this juncture, significant commercial development took place both in the East and in the New World. The Iberian union remained till 1640 when the Braganza dynasty in Portugal, was ushered in with the 1640 revolution against the Spanish Habsburgs. Joao IV became the new King of Portugal in December 1640. As a result, international trade around the world developed, reaching new heights between 1580 and 1640.

The European contact with Manila began as early as 1521 and Miguel Lopez de Legazpi, after the establishment of the Spanish colony, in his letters of 1568 and 1569 to Philip II, the King of Spain, praised the abundance of timber in the Philippines.1 Andres de Mirandaola in his letter of 1574 and Andres de San Nicolas, Luis de Jesus and Juan de la Conception in their accounts of 1624 commended highly the fertile forest in the Philippines, the prevalence of cinnamon trees, brasil-trees, small pomegranate trees and orange trees that had delicious fruits, besides the abundance of incorruptible woods, such as ebony, cedar, cypress and cedar.2 Andres de Mirandaola’s letter of 1574 and Francisco de Sande’s letter of 1576 mentioned the availability of suitable wood for shipbuilding in the Philippines for the naval purposes of the Spanish king.3 Juan Pacheco Maldonado wrote in his letter to King Philip II in 1575 that there was enough timber to construct three to four galleons each year, since Spain needed ships to defend her new possessions in the East.4 Santiago de Vera from Manila mentioned in 1586 that Filipinos had proven skill in building ships of all kinds owing to abundance of wood.5 Several ships were built at Masbate, Marinduque, Camarines and Albay while new shipyards came to be established at Cavite and Oton. By 1616, six out of the seven galleons stationed in Manila for its defense, were built in the Philippines. These large ships required continual repair due to wartime losses and frequency of the shipwrecks that took place. There was also the need to replace timber in the tropical waters.6 The large scale endeavour of shipbuilding and repairs in the Philippines had therefore to be carried out by a vast amount of labour that was required. The municipalities had begun to provide people to work in the shipyards.7 Hernando de Los Rios Coronel in 1621 mentioned that manpower was required in the Philippines and the masts of one galleon involved the efforts of 6,000 Filipinos for 3 months, simply to supply and transport the wood.8

In the wake of the circumstances stated above, the royal officials recommended the purchase of slaves from India to Manila, in as early as 1584 and again 1597, who could serve as caulkers and carpenters for the King’s ships. This was viewed in a way to save huge expenditure incurred on the salaries paid.9

PRIVATE PORTUGUESE TRADERS AND SLAVE
TRADE FROM NAGAPATTINAM TO
MANILA, 1616-1689

Spanish records provide some notions of slavery, slave trade being conducted direct especially with physical contact. The sellers and buyers shared their ideas of servitude, rights and obligations. This writer has carefully avoided the slaves who had been exported from Goa, Cochin and Bengal in India, who were in Manila and later found their way to Mexico.10 One has included only the slaves hailing from the Tamil Coast. It is very easy to trace since Portuguese merchants and other slavers have often applied the region and caste names and also applied to the port of embarkation of slaves. Slaves were brought from the port and Portuguese settlement of Nagapattinam to Spanish Manila.

On 26 August 1616, Luis Danga, a resident of Dilao, purchased Jacinto, a Tamil slave captured during warfare by Benito Ferreira, a Portuguese man.11 Manuel Mamadu (Mohammed), a Tolucan (Muslim) slave who was Christianized had also been sold into slavery during the famine and he was shipped in 1622 along with slaves belonging to the caste of Reddis and other Tamils from Nagapattinam to Manila.12 The public defender of the slaves in Manila was able to persuade the court that Manuel’s captivity was illicit, while the other Tamil slaves who accompanied him in the ship to Manila posed no problems.13

Spanish records very often mention the castes of the Tamil slaves brought to Manila. One finds mention of paraiyar caste slaves.14 The records of 1619 mention the slaves of the valayars, the fishermen caste on the Tamil coast.15

In Nagapattinam the Portuguese private traders were able to acquire supplies of slaves from the area because some natives sold themselves into slavery due to famines. One has the testimony of a Hindu male of the paraiyar caste named Mani (Meney in the record), who admitted that he had been forced to sell himself in 1620 to Francisco Macedo, a Portuguese merchant and captain, due to hunger. He revealed that he entered into slavery through the efforts of a Portuguese broker called Joto Carin. The vicar general of the church of Our Lady of Immaculate Conception in the Portuguese settlement of Nagapattinam wrote that he examined the slave named Meney 25 years old and was fully convinced the sale was good. The missionary had then cleared the buyer’s conscience and gave him a license to sell Meney as a slave.16 It is a fact that slave traders began to use such a process that was ostensibly meant to provide slaves with some legal recourse to their advantage.

The status of slaves brought from Nagapattinam to Manila had been settled by the court authorities in Manila. Andres Annaya, a 18-year old slave of paraiyar caste, was sold by a Portuguese trader to Diaz who lived in Manila. It was found in 1622 that Diaz was arguing before a judge in Manila defending the slaves he had purchased. He said that Andres Annaya was equal to others who belonged to the same caste of paraiyars and all of them including Andres Annaya were captured during war and made slaves. The judge in Manila delivered judgement and he confirmed the slavery of Andres Annaya.17

Spanish records mention the slaves of the Tamil communities in addition to migrants from Telugu country who had settled in the Tamil region under the nayaks of Vijayanagar empire. Manuel Reddi who spoke Telugu but also knew Tamil, having lived in the hinterland of Nagapattinam, had been purchased as a slave and was brought to Manila in a ship in 1631 along with the load of slave cargo that included Tamil men of vellalas (valala) caste.18

A record mentions that slaves were destined to reach Manila along with textile cargo under the Portuguese. The same ships returned carrying rich and large cargo of silver ingots which came from Mexico to Manila. In one instance in 1631 a Portuguese ship was captured by the Dutch and the rich cargo of silver bullion had become the property of the Dutch East India Company since the booty was not returned.19 Thus one finds slave trade was highly profitable.

The Portuguese missionaries were not in favour of slave trade and so the Portuguese viceroy in Goa took steps to control and he banned the slave trade. An order was issued in this regard prohibiting the sale of slaves in Nagapattinam and Tuticorin since 28 June 1632.20 However, slave trade by private Portuguese traders thrived secretly.

The Portuguese slave traders and their Spanish clients made more specific references to the social groups of slaves, mentioning particularly the castes. One finds continued references to Reddis and Vellalar slaves exported to Manila even during the year 1634.21

The caste names of Chettis are mentioned in Spanish records of 1634 and their ships had been also recorded. These traders were not slaves but whether they brought slaves or textiles had not been clear.22 Records continue to mention Tamil merchants trading in Manila even in the year 1685.23

The slaves brought from Nagapattinam were employed but their job description had been largely unknown. We find mention of serangs (saranguis) reaching Manila in 1634.24 Another record states that serang Dila and twelve lascars had reached Manila through the ship of Luis Dias a Portuguese merchant from Tamil Coast. On arrival in the Philippines they worked in the port of Cavite. It is found that the port officials had compensated Luis Dias for the work of the lascars. The inquisition officials boarding the ships had inspected them and they took note of heretical materials mentioning the religious affiliation of the lascars. It is found that a few of them belonged to the caste of paravars, the Christians of the pearl fishery while some of them were Muslims and Hindus.25 It had been mentioned that these maritime workers had brought to the Philippines a long tradition of seafaring and all of its associated and accumulated knowledge of sailing that they gained over the centuries. The tradition of lascar recruitment and service to staff the shipping necessitated the demand for employees in Manila. Vellalar slaves had continued to arrive in Manila in 1647 and they were used as slave labour.26 Antonio a Tamil slave brought from Nagapattinam in 1644 was sold for 318 pesos in Manila. The slave was found collecting forest products for the master.27

The Dutch Company officials on the Coromandel Coast pointed out the distinction between the slaves captured during the naval battles and wars fought between the Portuguese and the Dutch and the illegal kidnapping and stealing of men and women by the Portuguese private traders in Nagapattinam. In 1651, Carel Reniers (1650-3) the Dutch Governor General and his Council in Jakarta condemned the unbecoming Christian practices of the Portuguese in Nagapattinam who stole slaves from the hinterland of the ports at the dead of night. They also committed open robbery with the connivance of some natives around Nagapattinam who profited from slave trade. Taking these cases well in mind and on high moral grounds, the Dutch officials felt at that time that they should never imitate this great sin of the Portuguese who were stealing and kidnapping slaves even if the Dutch were to acquire more of them.28

Slaves abducted and captured were purchased and sold time and again owing to profit in slave trade. The slaves were exported by the Portuguese private traders from Nagapattinam to Manila. According to a report, there was a married Tamil male who came from Madurai to Nagapattinam exploring the possibility of finding some means of livelihood and employment to support his family. Having found some job at Nagapattinam he asked leave of absence after a month from the person with whom he was serving to go to Madurai and fetch his wife and children in 1662. After obtaining leave and necessary permission he proceeded and reached Madurai. There he learnt that the neighbour in Nagapattinam to whom he had entrusted his family had abducted them, telling the wife that her husband had sent for her. When he returned to Nagapattinam he learnt that his wife and sons were already sold and taken to Tranquebar and were resold treacherously to the Portuguese vicar-general for 30 pagodas and members of his family were not aware of it. In the end he came to the Danish settlement of Tranquebar and made efforts to recover them. When approached, the Portuguese priest at once resisted and reported the matter to Eskild Andersen the Danish Governor (1655-72). Further, the man himself was captured so that he could make no further attempts for his own release. Later, when he was released from the prison, the poor man lodged a complaint to the Bishop of Mylapore, but a hearing was refused out of regard for the said Portuguese priest. He submitted a petition then and prayed that he might at least have permission to re-marry, since the said priest had already bought his wife and sons. In the meantime, he learnt that his family members had again been sold for 60 pagodas and were ready to sail for Manila. At this time, all members of his caste assembled and undertook to pay the sale price of his wife and sons within one month, since this Tamil was a poor man. Even this did not work. The Governor had earlier decided that resold slaves should not be embarked in the ships leaving for Manila, thereupon the Portuguese priest was forced to take the wife and sons away. The priest had again managed to send them for re–sale elsewhere into the hands of the Hindu traders. The husband in desperation, changed his faith and returned to Hinduism, since he was unable to secure justice from the Christians.29 Thus one finds crimes committed in slave trade against public decency, morality and disorderly conduct and also against public justice and breach of trust. The distinction between legal means and illegal kidnapping and robbery of slaves by the Portuguese private traders in Nagapattinam was thus flexible in theory and practice.

Manila was under the ecclesiastical jurisdiction of Mexican inquisition and not under the Portuguese inquisition in Goa. The port officials in the Philippines had to verify the legal and illegal traffic as per rules. The officials checked for the forbidden materials being brought in the incoming ships. Portuguese private merchants in many cases who transported slaves illegally to the Philippines brought the slaves before an ecclesiastical judge in Manila, testifying that they had lost their titles. The cleric drew up a slave license, which the merchant then took to the secular flexible to further legitimize his enslavement.30

It is noticed that the Portuguese private traders who brought slaves from Nagapattinam in 1689 had brought with them the necessary papers showing that the slaves had been taken in the time of wars, which they presented to the competent judge on arrival in Manila.31 They were very shrewd in business because the Spanish legal system had a process by which a master or a slave could demand to review the legality of the enslavement at court. The governor appointed official in the Philippines titled ‘Defender general of the slaves brought to the city of Manila from India and other parts’ did not know the intricacies involved in the slave trade of the Portuguese since he was charged with merely presenting the petitions against their enslavement before the Alcalde Ordinario (mayor).

Portuguese presence in China was intensified with the founding of Macau, a Portuguese settlement by merchants between 1554 and 1557. In the following decades, Macau was gradually incorporated by the Portuguese crown. Some Tamil slaves were taken by the Portuguese to Macau. Ignacio Morales was a Portuguese merchant in Macau and he had purchased a Tamil slave called Antonio of the Shanar caste (casta Sena). Morales came to Manila later with his slave and in 1674, he sold his slave Antonio to Francisco Fresno, a Spaniard.32

Some Spaniards also commenced to trade with the ports of Coromandel. Spanish captains sent their ships to Madras and Porto Novo to obtain woven textiles owing to demand. Tamil merchants also visited the Philippines. In 1701, the royal treasurer of the Philippines in Manila granted a license to sail and return to a Tamil Muslim ship captain and merchant who hailed from the Coromandel Coast to bring textiles and slaves.33 Slave trade continued in Coromandel Coast as late as 1703, when a ship anchored in Manila Bay with a load of 70 Tamil slaves and some Bengali slaves.34

TAMIL SLAVES IN MANILA EMPLOYED
IN COCONUT PALM CULTIVATION, 1646

It is important to ask why the slaves were brought to Manila. This was owing to labour demand. Slave trade that commenced and flourished between the Philippines and Tamil ports resulted in the residence of a significant slave population of Tamils who were employed in positions that involved various types of odd jobs in central Luzon.

The Spaniards in Manila had introduced usage and cultivation of coconut palms.35 Sebastián Hurtado de Corcuera, the Spanish Governor in 1646, mandated the growing of abaca and coconut palms in all communities with the proper growing conditions. Abaca palms provided fibre for cordage and rigging used on the naval craft of the Philippines. Coconut palms provided oil for illumination and the production of pitch, as well as fibre and toddy. Slaves came to be employed in agriculture and horticulture. The slaves imported by the Portuguese were exempted from tax and the governor stipulated that these slaves would not even be written down on the list. Additionally, the mayor needed to verify that those officially exempted from tribute really earned this classification.

Tamil slaves also embraced Christianity over a period of time and they were converted. Baptism was administered to Juan and Joseph, the two adult (black Malabar) Tamil slaves on 15 April 1623. One finds Don Bernardino Balinguit the master of the slaves had served as the (padrino) godfather. Several Tamil slaves continued to be admitted to the Roman church as one finds in the parish records of Lubao between 1622 and 1648.36

Interestingly, one finds infant baptisms recorded only with the names of the mothers of the slaves. It suggests the possibility of illicit sexual activity, and even as concubines of masters. In a record of 3 October 1638, Juan de Ávalos served as the godfather of Rafael, the son of Lady Juana of Tamil origin. However the record does not mention the name of an unknown father.37 On 2 November 1648, Lazaro Gonzalo and Inés the Tamil lady sponsored the baptism of Simón, the son of Pedro a Tamil slave and María Vanalangin.

SPANISH TRADE FROM MANILA AND TAMIL
SLAVES TO COLONIAL MEXICO, 1527-1704

Slaves were exported from India to Portugal in the early days after the advent of Vasco da Gama. One finds mention of Tamil slaves who had reached Lisbon. It is found that the Spaniards who sailed to the West had taken the assistance and help of some of these persons and employed them as interpreters and cooks who had hailed from the port of Calicut located on the west coast of India.

TAMIL SLAVE WORKERS EMPLOYED BY
THE SPANIARDS, 1527-1551

In the course of sailing to the Americas it is mentioned that Megallan had commissioned Álvaro de Saavedra Cerón in 1527 to set sail from Zihuatanejo (present-day state of Guerrero) to cross the Pacific to land in Moluccas. He died at sea trying to find the route back to the Americas.38 It is mentioned that Cortés a native of Calicut had served Saavedra as an interpreter in Asia.39 This man was one of the few Asians who had been to Mexico before the establishment of the Galleon trade began by the Spaniards from Manila to Acapulco.

According to a document of 1540 which lists the possessions of Juan de Zumarraga, the first Bishop of Mexico (New Spain), one finds mention of his cook, a slave called Juan Núñez owned by the Bishop who came from the port of Calicut.40 It is also found that Antonio de Mendoza, first viceroy of New Spain had owned a slave from India in 1551.41

TAMIL SLAVES CROSSING THE PACIFIC AND
EMPLOYED IN COCONUT PALM TREE
PLANTATIONS IN MEXICO, 1619

With the establishment of the Manila Galleon sailing to Mexico, migration and slave trading activities had come to be widely developed. Initially slaves from India who were sent to Manila, found their way to New Acapulco in Mexico. Anton Thomas a Tamil slave was taken in the ship from Manila to Acapulco in 1602.42 Luis de Astete, a surgeon in Mexico City purchased Gaspar a Tamil slave. In 1614, there were 8 slaves who lived in Mexico City (besides 5 slaves from Cochin, 4 from Colombo and one from Gujarat). Many slaves had the same names and so they should not be confused. The masters who purchased them and the years when the transactions took place had to be seen carefully. We find the presence of many Asians arriving in Mexico with the development and the spread of plantations of coconut palm trees. Many free men had also come to work in the plantations of these trees, which eventually supplanted the traditional economy in Mexico. In one of the plantations which belonged to a Filipino immigrant in 1619, it is found that 5 Indians were employed.43

SALE AND RESALE OF TAMIL
SLAVES IN MEXICO

Captain Juan Chavaria the captain of the ship ‘San Luis’ purchased Andres a Tamil slave in Manila from a Portuguese trader for 57 pesos in 1622. The slave was taken to Mexico and he was sold in 1635 in Acapulco to Simon Lopez for 200 pesos.44 Manule Joao Alcantra, the sailor of the ship ‘Nuesta Senora del Rosario’ (Our Lady of Rosary) had purchased a Tamil slave named Gaspar in Manila in 1643. He sold the slave to Captain Pablo de Carrascosa who was sailing to Acapulco. Later one finds that the slave was sold again to Francisco de Araujo on arrival at Acapulco. Gaspar was again sold to Luis de Astete for 250 pesos. Thus sale and resale of slaves had often been conducted and it is a feature very common in Manila and Mexico.45

SALE AND RESALE OF A TAMIL SLAVE OF
UDAIYAR CASTE IN MANILA AND
MEXICO, 1643

The Spanish Philippines had a diverse slave population, war captives and foreign slaves from as far away as Portuguese India. On arrival in Mexico, slave owners and Spanish officials grouped them together, overlooked their social and linguistic differences and categorized them all as chinos. But in the records one finds mention of slaves with the mention of the word Malabar, since they spoke Tamil language besides caste name of the slaves. Most of the persons who entered colonial New Spain, including western Mexico, were slaves. The Spanish residents of Colima and western Mexico purchased these slaves in the city of Mexico and Acapulco.

A document from the municipal archives of Colima records that Juan de Venegas a Spanish captain in Manila purchased Ignacio a Tamil slave of Udaiyar caste (casta Vadoya). He took the slave with him when he travelled from the Philippines to Colima in Mexico. Ignacio was thereafter sold to Alonso de Valderrama, who travelled with the slave to Acapulco. Valderrama, in turn, sold Ignacio to Tomás García de Lozada. Finally Juan Beltrán de Allende, a resident of Mexico City purchased Ignacio after paying money to Tomás García de Lozada in 1643. Thus it is surprising to note that sale of Ignacio for the first time was held in Manila and resale of the same slave had been conducted thrice in Mexico.46

Vadugar slaves were transported from Manila to Mexico in 1643. They were employed at Colima.47 Thiyagu (Diego) a Tamil slave living in Mexico City asserted his condition as a subject of India and he was unlawfully enslaved. His owner claimed he had purchased Diego first in Goa and he presented several Portuguese witnesses who testified that all the natives from Portuguese India were slaves.48 Thus some exemplary evidences set the stage for the Mexico slave market and its nature of sale and resale passing slaves into many hands.

TAMIL SLAVES EMPLOYED IN TEXTILE
WORKSHOPS IN MEXICO

Tamil slaves worked mainly as domestic servants or in textile workshops (obrajes). Tamil slaves lived and died in Mexico and one finds information in the ecclesiastical notaries of death. The notary of the parish of the Sagrario in 1708 had documented the death and burial of Luis Pera, the Tamil (Malabar) black slave owned by Don Juan de Garay Coechea.49 The transpacific slave trade ended in 1672-3 with the prohibition of Asian slavery. As a result the number of Tamils and other Asian slave transportation from Manila to Mexico decreased.

To conclude, it may be said that the prisoners of war, declared as slaves were brought from Nagapattinam and sold in Manila by Private Portuguese merchants. However legal stamp as slaves were given by the Jesuit ecclesiastical authorities in Nagapattinam for transport overseas. The Spanish authorities in Manila also examined the status of the slaves at the time of purchase and sale in the court because they promoted the slave trade. Manila slave market gave further way to voyages of slaves to Mexico. The great ships of the Manila Galleon thus linked the Spanish Philippines to the rest of the empire. During the seventeenth century countless slaves from culturally diverse communities including Tamils were brought in the ships of the Manila Galleon to Mexico.

NOTES

1. Miguel Lopez de Legazpi’s letter dated 26 June 1568 to King Philip II, in Emma Helen Blair, James Alexander Robertson, eds., The Philippine Islands, 1493-1898, 55 vols., Arthur H. Clark Company, Cleveland, Ohio, 1903-7 (hereafter Blair and Robertson), vol. II, pp. 232-43, see p. 242; Miguel Lopez de Legazpi, ‘Relation of the Philippine Islands dated 7 July 1569’, in Blair and Robertson, vol. III, pp. 54-61, see p. 59.

2. Andres de Mirandaola’s letter dated 8 January 1574 to King Philip II, in Blair and Robertson, vol. III, pp. 223-9, see p. 225; Andres de San Nicolas, Luis de Jesus, and Juan de la Conception, ‘General History of the Discalced Augustinian Fathers’, in Blair and Robertson, vol. XXI, 1624, pp. 111-318, see pp. 197, 227.

3. Andres de Mirandaola’s letter dated 8 January 1574 to King Philip II. Ibid., p. 225; Francisco de Sande, ‘Relation of the Filipinas Islands’, written from Manila dated 7 June 1576, in Blair and Robertson, vol. IV, pp. 21-97, see p. 59.

4. Juan Pacheco Maldonado’s letter of 1575 from Manila to King Philip II, in Blair and Robertson, vol. III, pp. 295-303, see p. 303.

5. Santiago de Vera, ‘Memorial to the Council by Citizens of the Filipinas Islands from Manila dated 26 July 1586’, in Blair and Robertson, vol. VI, pp. 157-233, see p. 206.

6. Sebastian de Pineda, ‘Philippine Ships and Shipbuilding’, in Blair and Robertson, vol. XVIII, 1619, pp. 169-88, see pp. 173, 180; Juan de Medina, ‘History of the Augustinian Order in the Filipinas Islands’, in Blair and Robertson, vol. XXIV, 1630, pp. 29-182; Sebastian Hurtado de Corcuera’s letter to King Philip II dated 11 July 1636, in Blair and Robertson, vol. XXVI, pp. 265-90.

7. San Pablo, ‘Compulsory service by the Indians’, in Blair and Robertson, vol. XIX, 1620, pp. 71-6; Nicholas Cushner, Spain in the Philippines: From Conquest to Revolution, Quezon City, 1971, pp. 117-26.

8. Hernando de Los Rios Coronel, ‘Memorial y Relacion para su Magestad, Madrid’, in Blair and Robertson, vol. XIX, 1621, pp. 183-298, see p. 203.

9. Archivo General de Indias (hereafter AGI), Seville, Spain, Seccion Filipinas, 29-50, 230r-232v (1584), AGI, Filipinas, 29-63, 427r-428v (1597), Carta de los oficiales de la Real Hacienda de Filipinas . . . proponen sustituir a los calafates y carpinteros de naos por esclavos de la India que sepan esos oficios, para ahorrar el salario que se les paga.

10. AGI, Filipinas, 10, R. 1, N. 25 (Masulipatnam, 1672); Archivo General de la Nación de México—Distrito Federal, México (hereafter AGN), Historia, 406, fls. 188r-191v (1616, 1674, Cochin); National Archives of the Philippines, Manila, Protocolo de Manila, SDS 19763 (Sale of slave Diego purchased by Miguel de Salazar), fls. 14b-15 (1674).

11. AGN, Historia, 406, fls. 187r-192r (1616).

12. AGN, Civil, 680, N. 2, passim (1594); AGN, Jesuítas, IV-68, fl. 1r (1 August 1622, 31 August 1622).

13. AGN, Indiferente Virreinal, caja 1355, exp. 34, fls. 2r-3r (1631).

14. AGN, Jesuitas, IV-68, exp. 1, fls. 1r-1v (1616); Family History Library Genealogical Society of Utah—Salt Lake City, USA (hereafter FHLGSU), MF, no. 1126936, Lubao, Bautismos, item 1, fl. 44r (1629).

15. AGN, Historia, 407, fl. 274r (1619).

16. AGN, Seccion Jesuitas, 4-26.2 (1620).

17. AGN, Seccion Jesuitas, IV-50.

18. AGN, Indiferente Virreinal, caja (hereafter c.), 1355, exp. 34, fls.1r, 3r (1631).

19. Nationaal Archief (hereafter NA), Den Haag, MSS VOC, 1094, fls.79-79v, 88.

20. Historical Archives of Goa, Panaji (hereafter HAG), Mss Moncoes do Reino, Livro 19C, 67-70/5-2, fls. 95-6.

21. AGN, Indiferente Virreinal, c. 1355, exp. 36, fls. 1r-1v (1634).

22. AGN, Indiferente Virreinal, c. 1355, exp. 37, fls. 1r-1v (1634).

23. AGI, Contaduría 1245, Tercera Pieza, fl. 599v (1685).

24. AGI, Contaduría 1216, fl. 294v (1634).

25. AGN, Inquisición, v. 355, exp. 44, fl. 501r (1626) and AGI, Contaduría, 1233, 2a pieza, fl. 118r (1658).

26. AGI, Escribanía de Cámara, 441B, fl. 7825v (1647).

27. Déborah Oropeza, Los ‘indios chinos’ en la Nueva España: La inmigración de la nao de China, 1565-1700, Tesis de doctorado en historia, El Colegio de México, 2007, p. 126.

28. W. Ph. Coolhas, ed., Generale Missiven van de Gouverneurs-Generaal en Raden Aan Heren XVII der Verenigde Oostindische Compagnie, 9 vols., ’S Gravenhage, 1960–84 (hereafter GM), vol. II, p. 479.

29. Nicolao Manucci, Storio do Mogur or Mogul India, 4 vols., ed. William Irvine, repr., New Delhi, 1981, vol. III, pp. 128-9.

30. AGN, Historia, 407, fls.162r-164r (1616).

31. AGI, Filipinas, 25-1-46 (1689).

32. Consejo Superior de Investigaciones Científicas-Instituto Histórico (hereafter CSIC-IH), MF, no. 3534, unnumbered (18 September 1674).

33. AGI, Filipinas, 124, N. 10, fls. 13v-14v (1701).

34. AGI, Filipinas, 127, N. 17, fls. 3r-4r. fs. 30v-33v (1703).

35. AGI, Filipinas, 84, N. 46, fl. 1r (1585).

36. FHLGSU, MF, no. 1126936, Lubao Bautismos, San Agustín, 1621-48, 1660-1736, 1738-51, 1757-65, item 1, fl. 4r (1622); For Balinguit, FHLGSU, MF, no. 1126936, item 1, fl. 9v (1623); FHLGSU, MF, no. 1126951, Lubao Matrimonios, San Agustín, 1622-75, 1695-1835, item 1, fl. 4v (1622). For the marriage of Lindavin and Tayomin, see ibid., fl. 5r (1622). For Sebastián, FHLGSU, MF, no. 1126936, Lubao Bautismos, San Agustín, 162148, item 1, fl. 27r.

37. Juana Malabar, see FHLGSU, MF, no. 1126936, Lubao Bautismos, San Agustín, 1621-48, item 1, fl. 100r (1638); FHLGSU, no. 1126951, Lubao Matrimonios, San Agustín, 1622-75, 1695-1835, item 1, fl. 5v (1623); FHLGSU, MF, no. 1126936, Lubao Bautismos, item 1, fl. 41r (1628); FHLGSU, MF, no. 1126951, Lubao Matrimonios, item 1, fl. 51r (1634).

38. Martín Fernández de Navarrete, Viajes y descubrimientos españoles en el Pacífico: Magallanes, Elcano, Loaysa, Saavedra, Madrid, Maxtor, 2011, originally published in 1919, pp. 204-54. See also, Ione S. Wright, Voyages of Álvaro de Saavedra Cerón, 1527-29, Coral Gables, University of Miami Press, 1951.

39. Juan Gil, La India y el Lejano Oriente en la Sevilla del Siglo de Oro, Seville, Biblioteca de Temas Sevillanos, 2011, pp. 150-1.

40. Joaquín García Icazbalceta, Fray Juan de Zumárraga: Primer o bispo y arzobispo de México, Buenos Aires, Espasa-Calpe, 1952, p. 221.

41. Déborah Oropeza, Los indios chinos, p. 13.

42. AGI, Contaduria, 901-1601-2 fl. 57v.

43. Oropeza, Los indios chinos en la Nueva España, p. 98. It is found that there were also 115 slaves including 21 from Manila, Cebu, Pampanga, Cagayan, Zambales, and other places in the Philippines, 2 from Terrenate, and 2 from Papua.

44. AGN, Jesuitas, IV-50.

45. AGN, Historia, V-406, fl.74r-74v; V-407 fl. 274; V-407, fl. 327.

46. Archivo Histórico del Municipio de Colima, Colima, México (hereafter AHMC), sección B, c. 23, exp. 5, fls.1r-1v (1643).

47. AHMC, sección B, c. 23, exp. 4, f. 1f (1643).

48. Juan Gil, La India y el Lejano Oriente, pp. 240-1.

49. FHLGSU, MF, no. 35770, Asunción Sagrario Metropolitano, Defunciones de castas 1707-33, item 1, fl. 35r (1708).